Guide to the Moses family papers, 1859-1951
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Moses family papers 1859-1951
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Moses family
13.5 linear feet Extent: Approx. 10,125 Items
Family originally from Savannah, Georgia, and residents of New York City, whose members included drama critic Montrose J. Moses, his wife Dorothy Herne and other Herne sisters, and his sister, author Belle Moses. The collection primarily consists of manuscripts written by Belle Moses. The personal correspondence, clippings, and notes of Belle Moses, Montrose J. Moses, and Dorothy Herne also represent a substantial portion. There are also five scrapbooks assembled by the Herne sisters. Also included are photographs, negatives, diaries, doctor's visiting books (from Belle's father, M.J. Moses), and memorabilia such as pins, calling cards, programs, and other keepsakes. Print materials include literature, poetry, and textbooks published around the turn of the century.
RL.00916
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Materials are on deposit and are unprocessed.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Moses family papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a deposit in 1986.
Biographical Note
Montrose Jonas Moses (1878-1933) was a drama critic, journalist, and author of works on American and European drama and on children's literature. He was married to Dorothy Herne. His sister, Belle Moses, was the author of approximately thirty works written for children and adults on figures such as Louisa May Alcott, Charles Dickens, Lewis Carroll, and Paul Revere.
Collection Overview
The collection primarily consists of manuscripts written by Belle Moses. The personal correspondence, clippings, and notes of Belle Moses, Montrose J. Moses, and Dorothy Herne also represent a substantial portion. There are also five scrapbooks assembled by the Herne sisters. Also included are photographs, diaries, doctor's visiting books, and memorabilia, such as pins, calling cards, programs, and other keepsakes. Print materials include literature, poetry, and textbooks published around the turn of the century.
Subject Headings
Herne, Dorothy; Moses, Belle; Moses, Montrose Jonas, 1878-1934; Moses family; Authors, American -- Correspondence; Drama -- History and criticism; English literature -- History and criticism; Negatives; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Related Material
Montrose Jonas Moses Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Description of Collection
- Moses Family papers, 1859-1951, (9 boxes)
  - Dorothy Herne Moses personal letters (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1864 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia (Box 1)
  - Dr. M.J. Moses physician's visiting books, 1869, 1874 (Box 1)
    Probably Belle Moses's father, Monefiore J. Moses.
  - Belle Moses manuscript, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Montrose J. Moses correspondence, 1921-1928 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Katherine Chrystal Herne scrapbooks, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Dorothy Herne scrapbook, 1902 (Box 2)
  - Julie A. Herne scrapbooks, 1896-1898 (Box 2)
  - Print materials (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
  - Belle Moses manuscripts, 1905 (Box 3)
  - Montrose J. Moses ledgers, 1923-1934 (Box 3)
  - "Papa's poems," 1864 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, programs, clippings, class notes 1899-1924 (Box 3)
  - Print materials (Box 3)
  - Rose J. Moses correspondence, 1900-1916 (Box 3)
    Belle Moses's mother.
  - Montrose J. Moses correspondence, 1900-1906 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1860-1870 (Box 4)
  - Belle Moses manuscripts (Box 4)
  - Belle Moses correspondence, address books, receipts, 1860-1940 (Box 4)
  - Print Materials (Box 4)
  - Montrose J. Moses correspondence, 1890-1920 (Box 5)
  - Dorothy Herne correspondence and diary, 1903 (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Negatives (Box 5)
  - Mrs. Moses medical receipts (Box 5)
  - Belle Moses manuscripts and notes, 1890s (Box 5)
  - Belle Moses manuscripts, clippings, notes, 1900-1930 (Box 6)
  - Print materials (Box 6)
  - Belle Moses manuscripts, 1890-1900 (Box 7)
  - Belle Moses correspondence, clippings, notes, diary, 1900-1937 (Box 7)
  - Franklin Delano Roosevelt: The Minute Man of '33, by Belle Moses (Box 7)
  - Belle Moses manuscripts (Box 8)
  - Belle Moses correspondence, notes, book lists, clippings, 1892-1940 (Box 8)
  - Photographs (Box 8)
  - Card catalog (Box 9)
  - Belle Moses manuscripts (Box 9)
  - Belle Moses correspondence, notes, clippings, 1930s (Box 9)